Finding Aid for the Michael Sahl Score Collection, 1953-2009
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Michael Sahl Collection of Manuscript Scores, 1953-2009
Mus. Arc. 41
Sahl, Michael, 1934-
2 boxes, (43 items)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The collection contains 42 manuscript scores, many of them reproductions by photocopy or ozalid, and 3 compact discs containing mp3 audio files of 10 works.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Michael Sahl, 2009.
Accruals and Additions
Further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Michael Sahl was born on September 2, 1934 in Boston. In 1942, after his family moved to New York, he commenced his formal musical training. In 1947, he began studying with Israel Citkowitz and has cited the composer and critic as particularly instrumental in endowing him with a love for American popular music. As a result, Sahl's increased involvement with and interest in folk, blues, jazz and American popular vocal standards influenced much of his compositional output. He later studied at Amherst College and Princeton University, where his teachers included Roger Sessions and Milton Babbitt. He also worked with Lukas Foss, Luigi Dallapiccola and Aaron Copland.
Sahl's academic training at Princeton centered on 12-note and serial techniques. In 1957-58, he received a Fulbright Fellowship in Europe and spent the following few years overseas attempting to compose in a Modernist style, but eventually realized that his inclination to write tonal melodies was too strong to ignore. In 1963, Sahl returned to the USA and became active in folk-rock music circles. After serving as a Creative Associate at the State University of New York at Buffalo in 1965, he became the pianist and music director for Judy Collins. Following his departure from Collins in 1969, Sahl made his reputation as a composer of operas, musical shows, and instrumental works, several of which are written in a musical style dominated by the hybridization of Romanticism, jazz and rock. He became acclaimed as one of the earliest composers to write in a genre-blending style that successfully managed to straddle the boundaries between classical "new music," pop, rock, jazz, and musical theater.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains 42 manuscript scores, many of them reproductions by photocopy or ozalid, and 3 compact discs containing mp3 audio files of 10 works.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series:
I. Scores
II. Audio files
Container List
- Scores, 1953-2009, I.; Item 1-42
  Arranged in alphabetical order by uniform title.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- An anarchist dream: for 2 keyboards / M. Sahl. [2002], 1 ms. score (16 p.); 44 cm. (Box 1, Item 01)
    Photocopy of holograph. For one electric and one acoustic keyboard. Caption title.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Baby music Baby music '07 / Sahl. 2007., 1 ms. score (11 p.); 43 cm. (Box 1, Item 02)
    Photocopy of holograph. For soprano saxophone, tenor saxophone, trumpet, bass trombone, drum set, guitar, piano, violin, violoncello and double bass. Caption title. Includes a duplicate of p. 1 with p. 3 on verso. At end: ½0/07.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Blood ferry lecture / music, Michael Sahl; text, Margaret Yard. 1992., 1 ms. score ([18] p.); 43 cm. (Box 1, Item 03)
    Photocopy of holograph. For high voice (spoken and sung) and piano. English words; also printed as typescript text and containing cross-outs and emendations by the composer preceding score. Includes photocopy of typescript text (8 leaves). Contains minor revisions by composer in blue ink. At end: Sketch 7/16/92.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Blues for Margaret: for solo piano / Michael Sahl. 1991., 7 p. of ms. music; 43 cm. (Box 1, Item 04)
    2 photocopies of holograph; 2nd copy missing caption. At end: 10/24/91.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Cloud city: string quartet / Michael Sahl. c2006., 1 ms. score (15, 11, 16 leaves); 22 x 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 05)
    Computer-generated holograph. Caption title.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Cloud city walk / Sahl. c2004., 1 ms. score (50 p.); 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 06)
    Computer-generated holograph. For electric violin, electric guitar, synthesizer and double bass. Cover title. "For the New York Art Ensemble"--Caption.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Concerto, violin, instrumental ensemble Concerto for electric violin / Michael Sahl. 2001., 1 ms. score (35 p.); 22 x 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 07)
    Photocopy of holograph. For solo electric violin, soprano saxophone, tenor saxophone, trumpet, bass trombone, drum set, guitar, piano, electric viola, electric violoncello and double bass. Caption title. "(gypsy music)"--Caption, in composer's hand in pencil. "For Mary Rowell"--Caption. At end: 11/8/99, revised ½8/01.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Dancing in the landscapes / Michael Sahl. [1993], 1 ms. score (11 p.); 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 08)
    Computer-generated holograph. For string quartet. Caption title. Date from composer's Web site. "For the Sirius String Quartet"--Caption.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Doina / Michael Sahl. 1979., 1 ms. score (36 p.); 22 x 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 09)
    Photocopy of holograph. For violin, percussion, piano and double bass. Caption title. At end: April 11th, 1979 223 E. 5th Street. Contains minor revisions and other markings by the composer in pencil and ink.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Dumb, mixed solo voices Dumb / [music by] Michael Sahl; [text by] Margaret Yard. 2002., 1 ms. score (5 p.); 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 10)
    Computer-generated holograph. For 2 sopranos, mezzo-soprano, 2 contraltos and tenor, unaccompanied. English words. Caption title. At end: Michael Sahl 05/16/02 for Boudewijn Buckinx.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Dumb, sopranos (5), tenor Dumb / [music by] Michael Sahl; [text by] Margaret Yard. 2002., 1 ms. score (4 leaves); 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 11)
    Holograph (Ink). For 5 sopranos and tenor, unaccompanied. English words; also printed as typescript text following score. Title from holograph caption. "(Correction)"--Holograph caption, in composer's hand in pencil. Contains revisions in pencil and ink on a pasted insert and using white correction fluid applied directly to manuscript. At end of holograph: Michael Sahl 1/16/02 for Boudewijn Buckinx. Includes two photocopies of p. 1 and one complete photocopy (4 p.) of holograph. Includes ms. sketch in pencil (1 leaf).
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- The exiles' café / Michael Sahl. 1984., 1 ms. score ([44] p.); 44 cm. (Box 1, Item 12)
    Photocopy of holograph. For clarinet, tenor saxophone, trumpet, percussion, piano, violin and double bass. Contains 88 leaves photocopied onto [44] p. "For the Allbright-Knox [i.e. Albright-Knox] Gallery"--Caption. At end: July 7th, 1984 223 E. 5th St. New York.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Exiles' café. Tango; arr. Tango from "The exiles' café" / Michael Sahl. 1984., 5 leaves of ms. music; 22 x 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 13)
    2 photocopies of holograph. Orig. for clarinet, tenor saxophone, trumpet, percussion, piano, violin and double bass; arr. for piano solo. Caption title. At end: 11/6/84.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Fire song / Michael Sahl. 1996., 1 ms. score (55 p.); 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 14)
    Photocopy of holograph. For soprano saxophone, tenor saxophone, trumpet, bass trombone, drum set, guitar, piano, violin, violoncello, and double bass. Caption title. Contains 110 leaves photocopied onto 55 p. At end: 6/19/96.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Grand sonata: for violin & piano / Michael Sahl. 1999., 1 ms. score (13 p.); 44 cm. (Box 1, Item 15)
    Photocopy of holograph. Caption title. Contains 26 leaves photocopied onto 13 p. "For Mary Rowell"--Caption.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Heartsplit tundra / [music by] Michael Sahl; [text by] Margaret Yard. [2008], 1 ms. score (4 leaves); 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 16)
    Photocopy of holograph. For high voice and piano. English words. Caption title. Contains revisions by the composer using white correction fluid applied directly to manuscript.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Home / [music by] Michael Sahl; [text by] Margaret Yard. [2008], 1 ms. score (4 leaves); 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 17)
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- In the woods / Michael Sahl. 1984., 1 ms. score (34 p.); 22 x 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 18)
    Holograph in pencil. For clarinet, piano, violin and double bass. Caption title. At end: Nov. 1, 1984 223 E 5 St NYC. Contains noticeable erasures and revisions by the composer in pencil.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Instrumental music. Selections 3 pieces for band / Michael Sahl. 2007., 1 ms. score (15, 15, 11 p.); 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 19)
    2 photocopies of holograph. All works for soprano saxophone, tenor saxophone, trumpet, bass trombone, drum set, guitar, piano, violin, violoncello and double bass. Cover title. Although bound together with a collective title on the cover, these works are listed separately in the composer's own list of works. Contains 82 leaves photocopied onto 41 p. Contains minor emendations by the composer in pencil. At end: 8/25/07 (1st work); 9/7/07 (2nd work); 11/27/07 (3rd work). Old strollers -- In the dark -- Apatrides.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Jungles / Sahl. 1990., 1 ms. score (40 p.); 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 20.)
    Photocopy of holograph. For electric violin, electric guitar, drum set, piano and double bass. Caption title. Contains 80 leaves photocopied onto 40 p. At end: Dec. 17, 1990; bottom of p. 3: 12/1/90; bottom of p. 24: ½9/90.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Katrina: voices of the lost / [music by] Michael Sahl; [text by] Margaret Yard. 2006., 1 ms. score ([36] p.); 44 cm. (Box 1, Item 21)
    Photocopy of holograph. Cantata for SATBar, percussion, piano and synthesizer. English words. Caption title. Contains 70 leaves photocopied onto [36] p. At end: 04/13/06. Contains revisions and other markings by the composer in pencil.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Lord of my love / Michael Sahl; [text by] Wm. Shakespeare. 1956., 1 ms. score (2 leaves); 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 22)
    Holograph in ink on vellum. For high voice and piano. English words. Received with another song, That time of the year, in folder marked "Shakespeare songs". "Nov. 13, 1956"--Caption.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Millay songs / [music by] Michael Sahl; [text by] Edna Millay. [1956], 1 ms. score (5 leaves); 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 23)
    Holograph in pencil on vellum. For soprano and piano. English words. Title from enclosing manila folder. Thou art not lovelier than lilacs -- I being born a woman and distressed.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Milltown gypsy ball; arr. The milltown gypsy ball / Michael Sahl. 1986., 1 ms. score (32 p.); 22 x 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 24)
    Photocopy of holograph. Orig. for violin solo and winds; arr. for two string quartets (1st violin of quartet A is solo violin), drum set and double bass. Caption title. "Commissioned by Mary Rowell and the Vermont Youth Orchestra"--Caption. "Arranged for String Fever"--Caption. At end: July 19, 1986 Lake Eaton Campground New York. Contains minor emendations by the composer in pencil and ink.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- A mitzvah for the dead: concerto for violin + tape / [Michael Sahl]. [1966], 11 p. of ms. music; 33 cm. (Box 1, Item 25)
    Reverse photoreproduction of holograph. Title from enclosing envelope. "Masters"--Enclosing envelope. Fourth movement entitled "Var's [i.e. variations] on Last Rose of Summer."
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Old strollers / [Michael Sahl]. 2007., 1 ms. score (15 p.); 44 cm. (Box 1, Item 26)
    Photocopy of holograph. For soprano saxophone, tenor saxophone, trumpet, bass trombone, drum set, guitar, piano, violin, violoncello and double bass. Caption title. Contains 30 leaves photocopied onto 15 p. At end: 8/25/07.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Prothalamium / [music by] Michael Sahl; [text by] Aaron Kramer. 1953., 1 ms. score (4 leaves); 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 27)
    Photocopy of holograph. For baritone and piano. English words. Caption title.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Quartets, strings (1957) String quartet 1957 / Michael Sahl. 1957., 1 ms. score (61 p.); 33 cm. (Box 1, Item 28)
    Ozalid copy of holograph. "To Mara"--T.p. At end: January 8, 1957.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Quartets, strings (2000) String quartet 2000 / Michael Sahl. 2000., 1 ms. score (22 p.); 22 x 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 29)
    Photocopy of holograph. Caption title. At end: 5/23/00.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Screen song / [music by] Michael Sahl; [text by] Margaret Yard. [2008], 1 ms. score (12 p.); 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 30)
    Photocopy of holograph. For high voice and piano. English words. Caption title. Contains pencil markings by the composer.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Serenades, piano Serenades for piano solo, 1994 / Sahl. 1994., 19 p. of ms. music; 44 cm. (Box 1, Item 31)
    Photocopy of holograph. At end: 7/1/94.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Sonatas, piano (1972) Piano sonata / Michael Sahl. 1972., 20 p. of ms. music; 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 32)
    Photocopy of holograph. Caption title. Includes duplicate copy (20 p. photocopied onto [10] p.; 22 x 28 cm.) of holograph. At end: November 2, 1972, 82 E 3 St New York N.Y.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Songs (1957) 3 songs / Michael Sahl; poems of Gerard Manley Hopkins. 1957., 1 ms. score (17 leaves); 44 cm. (Box 1, Item 33)
    Photocopy of ms. For soprano and piano. English words. Cover title. "December, 1957"--Cover. The windhover -- Carrion comfort -- To R.B.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Songs (1990) Two songs / [music by] Michael Sahl; [text by] Margaret Yard. [1990], 1 ms. score (18 p.); 28 x 44 cm. (Box 1, Item 34)
    Photocopy of holograph. For high voice and piano. English words. Title from bottom of p. 1. Contains 36 leaves photocopied onto 18 p. The old ones -- Last day years end.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Songs (1990) Two songs / [music by] Michael Sahl; [text by] Margaret Yard. 1990., 1 ms. score (9, 15 leaves); 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 35)
    Photocopy of holograph. For high voice and piano. English words. Includes photocopy of typescript text ([3] leaves). Cover title. "Master"--Enclosing envelope. "2 songs revised"--Enclosing envelope. Contains revisions using a pasted insert and white correction fluid applied directly to manuscript. Os velhos = The old ones -- Last day year's end.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Storms / Michael Sahl. 1985., 1 ms. score (55 p.); 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 36)
    Photocopy of holograph. For saxophone quartet (soprano, alto, tenor and baritone) and string quartet. Caption title. "For the Amherst Saxophone Quartet, 1985"--Caption. At end: 6/13/85, 223 E 5 St NYC.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Strangers in the land of Beulah: based on the old hymn, written for Ma Prem Alimo / Michael Sahl. 1982., 1 ms. score (14 p.); 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 37)
    Photocopy of holograph. For high voice and piano. English words. Caption title. At end: ½9/82, 223 E. 5 St NYC.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Symphonies, instrumental ensemble Symphony 1983 / Michael Sahl. 1983., 1 ms. score (48 leaves); 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 38)
    Photocopy of holograph. For clarinet, tenor saxophone, flugelhorn, bass trombone, electric guitar, drum set, piano, electric violin, and double bass. Caption title. At end: March 22, 1983, 223 E 5 St. NYC. "Symphony 1983 score 8 ½ x 11 submaster"--Enclosing envelope.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Symphonies (1988) Symphony 1988 / Michael Sahl. 1988., 1 ms. score (97 p.); 23 x 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 39)
    Photocopy of holograph. At end: 10/14/87, 223 E 5 St NY. Original title, Symphony 1987, visible in caption beneath label containing revised title.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- That time of year / Michael Sahl; [text by] Wm. Shakespeare. 1956., 1 ms. score (3 leaves); 36 cm. (Box 1, Item 40)
    Holograph in ink on vellum. For high voice and piano. English words. Received with another song, Lord of my love, in folder marked "Shakespeare songs". "Nov. 11, 1956"--Caption.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Volcano pie / Michael Sahl. 2006., 1 ms. score (24 p.); 44 cm. (Box 1, Item 41)
    Photocopy of holograph. For soprano saxophone, tenor saxophone, trumpet, bass trombone, electric guitar, drum set, piano, electric violin, electric violoncello and electric bass. Caption title. Contains 48 leaves photocopied onto 24 p. At end: 11/14/06.
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- A walk: for 2 keyboards / [Michael Sahl]. [2000], 1 ms. score (12 p.); 41 cm. (Box 1, Item 42)
    Photocopy of holograph. For one electric and one acoustic keyboard. Contains crossouts and revisions in pencil.
- Audio files, 2009, II.; Item 43
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Selections [Music by Michael Sahl]. [2009], 3 sound discs: digital; 4 3/4 in. (Box 1, Item 43)
    MP3 files. The 1st-5th, 10th works for instrumental ensemble; the 6th for piano, guitar, percussion, violin and double bass; the 7th for string quartet; the 8th for violin and piano; the 9th a cantata for SATBar, piano, percussion and synthesizer. The 9th work sung in English. Title supplied by cataloger. Text of the 9th work by Margaret Yard. Unknown performers. Recording dates and locations unknown. Compact discs. [Disc 1]. Fire song; Baby music; Old strollers; In the dark; Apatrides; Jungles -- [Disc 2]. Quartet 2000; Grand sonata for violin and piano -- [Disc 3]. Katrina: voices of the lost; Volcano pie.
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Subjects
Sahl, Michael, 1934- --Manuscripts; Music--Manuscripts
Genres
Scores
Associated Material
Additional Guides
All scores in the collection are cataloged in WorldCat and are available in BISON, the online catalog for the University at Buffalo Libraries, by performing a "Title begins with" search under "Michael Sahl Score Collection".